# Cristóbal Sifón

Profesor Auxiliar Instituto de Física, Facultad de Ciencias Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso Casilla 4059, Valparaíso, Chile

E-mail: cristobal.sifon@pucv.cl Phone: +56 (32) 227 4698

https://github.com/cristobal-sifon/

### Research Interests

My research focuses on galaxy cluster physics including observable—mass scaling relations for cosmological analyses, brightest cluster galaxies, the mass content of cluster galaxies, and merging clusters. I am also interested in intrinsic galaxy alignments, both as contaminants for cosmic shear and as a physical mechanism in their own right. I use various tools and techniques to study these phenomena, including weak gravitational lensing, spectroscopy, the exploitation of optical surveys in general, and most recently also of hydrodynamical simulations.

**Collaborations:** 4MOST Chilean Cluster Galaxy Evolution Survey (CHANCES) — 4MOST Hemisphere Survey (4HS) — Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT) — Canadian Cluster Comparison Project (CCCP) — Galaxy Cluster Mass Reconstruction Project — Kilo-Degree Survey (KiDS) — Legacy Survey of Space and Time Dark Energy Science Collaboration (LSST-DESC) — Multi-Epoch Nearby Cluster Survey (MENeaCS) — Simons Observatory.

# **Employment**

[2022 - Present] Profesor Auxiliar, Pontificia Universidad Católica de Valparaíso (PUCV), Chile

[2019 - 2022] Profesor Asociado, PUCV

[2016 - 2019] Postdoctoral Research Associate, Princeton University, USA

### **Education**

[2012 - 2016] Ph.D. Astrophysics, Universiteit Leiden, The Netherlands

[2010 - 2012] M.Sc. Astrophysics, P. Universidad Católica de Chile (PUC), Chile

[2005 - 2010] B.Sc. Astronomy, PUC

# **Teaching & Mentoring**

## **Graduate Research Mentoring**

[2023 - Present] Javier Urrutia, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2020 - 2022] Camila Aros, PUCV: MSc thesis advisor.

[2017 – 2019] Naomi Robertson, Oxford University (UK): co-advised PhD thesis project (Advisor: Joanna Dunkley).

[2013 – 2014] Joshua Albert, Universiteit Leiden: co-advised MSc thesis project (Advisor: Huub Röttgering).

#### **Undergraduate Research Mentoring**

[2022] Pablo Garrido, PUCV: Undergraduate Senior thesis.

[2021] Lya Marmolejo, PUCV: Undergraduate summer research project (USRP) and Senior thesis.

[2020] Nicole Mejía, Universidad Nacional Autónoma de Honduras (Honduras): Four-month undergraduate research project through the Central American-Caribbean Bridge in Astrophysics Program (URL).

[2020] Felipe Jorquera, PUCV: USRP.

[2018] Malik Walker, Princeton University: USRP and Junior Project.

## **Courses Taught**

**Graduate:** Data Analysis (2023), Techniques of Observational Astrophysics (2022), Observational Cosmology (2020-2021)

Undergraduate: Astronomical Instrumentation (2023), Galactic Astronomy (2021-2022), Programming (2020-

2022), Cosmology (2020)

**Non-astrophysics major:** Basic Astronomy for Engineers (2022)

## **Grants**

[2020] ALMA-ANID Fund to hire a postdoc (Co-PI, 2 years, US\$77,000)

[2019] FONDECYT Iniciación research grant (PI, 3 years, US\$125,000)

## Successful Observing Proposals (as PI)

I have been the PI of 12 successful observing proposals totalling hundreds of observing hours in optical (Gemini-South/GMOS, VST/OmegaCAM), near-infrared (Magellan/Fourstar), submm (APEX/CONCERTO), and radio (GMRT, VLA) telescopes.

**Observing Experience:** I have spent roughly 180 hours observing with optical (Gemini South/GMOS) and near-infrared (NTT/Sofl, Magellan/Fourstar) instruments performing both imaging and spectroscopy of galaxy clusters.

# **Community Activity**

**Journals:** I have served as a referee for Astronomy & Astrophysics, The Astrophysical Journal, Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, and Nature Astronomy.

**Telescope Allocation Committees (TACs):** I have served as a reviewer for the Canadian and Swiss National Foundation TACs, as well as for the *Chandra* X-ray Observatory.

#### Informal courses

[2016] Making Better Figures, Universiteit Leiden (see here)

#### Press articles authored

[July 2017] Galaxy clusters: Falling into line (Nature Astronomy News & Views)

[July 2013] Featured Science: Dynamical masses of galaxy clusters discovered with the Sunyaev-Zel'dovich effect (Gemini Focus)

#### Outreach

[2022] Interview for Radio Valentín Letelier, Valparaíso, to talk about CHANCES.

[2021] Online public talk in the conext of the Chilean Day of Astronomy.

[2018 – 2019] Assisted with Public Astronomical Observations in Spanish, Princeton University.

[2013 - 2014] Assisted with Public Observations at the Old Observatory, Leiden Observatory.

[2012] Co-taught an Astronomy Course for Seniors, PUC.

[2011] Participated in *Starry Nights*, observation nights for elementary and middle school students in social risk organized by ESO-Santiago.

[2010] Invited talk on board the "FFG14 Almirante Latorre" Chilean Navy ship, Valparaíso, Chile.

[2010] The Universe, a series of talks for elementary school students in social risk organized by PUC.

## Technical skills

I am an experienced python programmer, and I also have some experience with IRAF/PyRAF. I have written pygmos, a Python/PyRAF pipeline to reduce Gemini-GMOS spectra which is available here. I also developed

an early analysis pipeline for the FLAMINGOS-II infrared imager and spectrograph installed in the Gemini-South telescope. I am one of three lead developers and maintainers of the galaxy-galaxy lensing pipeline used by the KiDS collaboration (written in python, but which is not public at the moment). Other codes I have written are posted at my github page.

# Other Work Experience

[2007 – 2008] Ski instructor at Homewood Mountain Ski Resort in Lake Tahoe, CA. Obtained certification as Level I Ski Instructor by the Professional Ski Instructors of America (PSIA).

[2006 - 2007] Ski lift operator at Sun Valley Resort, Sun Valley, ID.

## References

Prof. Henk Hoekstra (*PhD advisor*)
Leiden Observatory, Universiteit Leiden
Niels Bohrweg 2, NL-2333 CA Leiden, The Netherlands
Phone: +31 (71) 527 5594

E-mail: hoekstra@strw.leidenuniv.nl

Prof. David N. Spergel

Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute 160 Fifth Avenue, 7th Floor, New York, NY 10010, USA

Phone: +1 (646) 654 0066

E-mail: dns@astro.princeton.edu

• Prof. John P. Hughes

Department of Physics and Astronomy, Rutgers University 136 Frelinghuysen Rd., Piscataway, NJ 08854, USA

Phone: +1 (848) 445 8878

E-mail: jph@physics.rutgers.edu

Prof. L. Felipe Barrientos (MSc advisor)
Instituto de Astrofísica, P. Universidad Católica de Chile
Casilla 306, Santiago 22, Chile
Phone: +56 (2) 2354 4941

7 Holle: | 50 (2) 2551 1511

E-mail: barrientos@astro.uc.cl

• Prof. Felipe Menanteau

Department of Astronomy, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

1002 W. Green St., Urbana, IL 61801, USA

Phone: +1 (217) 244 6297 E-mail: felipe@illinois.edu